Burges Green Cartoons
Burges Green Cartoons
1949-1970
Green, Burges.
21.25 linear ft.
Over 4,800 original editorial cartoons drawn for the Providence Journal.
149020
Biographical History
Burges Green (1912-1981) was an American editorial cartoonist.
Green was born June 16, 1912 and was the nephew of U.S. Senator Theodore Green of Rhode Island. Green worked for the Providence Journal as editorial cartoonist until 1970. He also illustrated "American Literature in Parody: A Collection of Parody, Satire and Literary Burlesque of American Writers Past and Present" (Twayne 1955)
Green died in June 1981.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Burges Green Cartoons consist entirely of editorial cartoons documenting national, international and local politics.
The Cartoons series contains approximately 4,845 original editorial cartoons from 1949 to 1970 and one proof.
Items typically measure 12 1/4" x 17 1/2". Green worked in ink, primarily on Craftint paper. Traces of pencil are visible; captions and date information appear in blue pencil. Green's style emphasized thin lines and little shading; a limited number of cartoons feature crayon shading.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Green, Burges.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeevich, 1894-1971 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Stalin, Joseph, 1879-1953 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Providence Journal Company.; Providence journal.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Caricatures and cartoons -- Rhode Island -- Providence.; Civil rights movements -- United States -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cold War -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Rhode Island -- Providence.; Editorial cartoons -- Rhode Island -- Providence.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Providence Journal Company, 1970.
Inventory
- Cartoons, Click here for a detailed inventory.
  - 1949 Dec-1950 Jun (Oversize 38)
  - 1950 Jul-Dec, 1950 (Oversize 39)
  - 1951 Jan-Jun (Oversize 1)
  - 1951 Jul-Dec (Oversize 2)
  - 1952 Jan-Jun (Oversize 3)
  - 1952 Jul-Dec (Oversize 4)
  - 1953 Jan-Jun (Oversize 5)
  - 1953 Jul-Dec (Oversize 6)
  - 1954 Jan-Jun (Oversize 7)
  - 1954 Jul-Dec, October 31 cartoon is located in mapcase 1, drawer 107 (Oversize 8)
  - 1955 Jan-Jun (Oversize 9)
  - 1955 Jul-Dec (Oversize 10)
  - 1956 Jan-Jun (Oversize 11)
  - 1956 Jul-Dec, October 28 cartoon is located in mapcase 1, drawer 107 (Oversize 12)
  - 1957 Jan-Jun (Oversize 13)
  - 1957 Jul-Dec, 1957 (Oversize 14)
  - 1958 Jan-Jun (Oversize 15)
  - 1958 Jul-Dec, 1958 (Oversize 16)
  - 1959 Jan-Jun (Oversize 17)
  - 1959 Jul-Dec, 1959 (Oversize 18)
  - 1960 Jan-Jun (Oversize 19)
  - 1960 Jul-Dec, 1967 (Oversize 20)
  - 1961 Jan-Jul (Oversize 21)
  - 1961 Aug-1962 Feb, 1961 (Oversize 22)
  - 1962 Mar-Sep (Oversize 23)
  - 1962 Oct-1963 Mar, 1962 (Oversize 24)
  - 1963 Apr-Sep (Oversize 25)
  - 1963 Oct-1964 Mar (Oversize 26)
  - 1964 Apr-Sep (Oversize 27)
  - 1964 Oct-1965 Mar, 1964 (Oversize 28)
  - 1965 Apr-Oct (Oversize 29)
  - 1965 Nov-1966 Apr (Oversize 30)
  - 1966 May-Dec (Oversize 31)
  - 1967 Jan-Jun (Oversize 32)
  - 1967 Jul-1968 Feb, 1967 (Oversize 33)
  - 1968 Mar-Sep (Oversize 34)
  - 1968 Oct-1969 Mar, 1968 (Oversize 35)
  - 1969 Apr-Oct (Oversize 36)
  - 1969 Nov-1970 Mar, circa 1960s (Oversize 37)
  - Undated, 49 items (Oversize 40)